Today's דף daf is דף daf eighty-nine thank you. and we are
we are about to start a
משנה mishna I believe.
No we are where are we? Oh no no I'm sorry okay
right thank you. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara picks up with oh yes we were having that
very fascinating debate about what happens
when you שחט shecht an animal שלא לשמה shelo lishma so we
know from זבחים Zevachim that it was like the staple of זבחים
Zevachim that it was כשר kosher but its owners do not fulfill
their obligation but of course here the גמרא Gemara and again I
always find this fascinating we went through an entire מסכת זבחים masechet
Zevachim and we're finding a key piece of the discussion here at
the end of מנחות. Menachot. The question is how much does it
sort of become like a generic קרבן korban or how much does
it retain its identity? And the way the גמרא Gemara is framing
the question is if that if you שחט shecht the אשם asham
of a מצורע metzora שלא לשמה shelo lishma how much do you
still have to bring its מנחה mincha with it? Because a normal
אשם מצורע asham metzora without its מנחה mincha is invalid. And here
is it still considered an אשם asham of a מצורע metzora but
it doesn't work for him? Or is once it's not working for
him it doesn't have that identity? So the
statement was yes you still have to bring its מנחה mincha it
still has its identity and without it's invalid. So then גמרא Gemara
says you know but is that true then ask about other things
like if you שחט shecht the עולה ola that comes with the
עומר omer which normally gets a double מנחה. mincha. If you did
it שלא לשמה shelo lishma would we say you still have to
do the double מנחה? mincha? Which means clearly the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that when it's שלא לשמה shelo lishma it becomes more of
a generic קרבן korban and not so much of the particular I
mean obviously it's still an עולה ola still a שלמים shelamim but
it's not of the exact particular nature. So the first answer was
אי הכי נמי ain hachi nami when you שחט shecht something even
שלא לשמה shelo lishma it remains its particular nature and you have
to do all the details. You bring all the parts of it.
You bring all the parts, you treat it totally normal. Nobody fulfills
it's like a free will sacrifice meaning nobody fulfills an obligation but
the קרבן korban is
still put on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay so רב אבא אמר Rav
Abba amar or רבא אמר
Rava amar בשלמא הני עולות נינהו. bishlama hanach olot ninhu. No no
no all the other cases that the גמרא Gemara asked about about
the תמיד tamid שלא לשמה shelo lishma or the lamb that comes
with the עומר omer שלא לשמה shelo lishma those are all עולות.
olot. eighty-nine עמוד א amud aleph לא חזי לעולת חובה קרבי לעולת
נדבה.
lo chazi le-olat chova karvi
le-olat nedava.
If they can't work for the obligatory עולה ola like for the
תמיד tamid or for the lamb that comes with the עצרת atzeret
then they can be a free will עולה. ola. Meaning there they
can shift to a generic identity. Generic I don't mean קרבן korban
that degree of generic but עולה ola generic עולה ola generic שלמים
shelamim right? So if I bring an עולה ola my עולה ola
שלא לשמה shelo lishma it can become a generic עולה. ola. If
I bring the עולה ola with the עומר omer שלא לשמה shelo
lishma it becomes generic so I no longer bring a double מנחה
mincha for the עומר omer I bring the normal מנחת נסכים minchas
nesachim because yes it does lose its identity and it can become
generic. That is true normally שלא לשמה shelo lishma it doesn't have
its very particular identity. It's still an עולה ola but it's a
generic עולה ola let's say or שלמים shelamim but a generic שלמים.
shelamim. So the some of the very if it's very distinctive like
the עולה ola that comes with the עומר omer that distinctiveness would
be lost. That normal. But the אשם מצורע asham metzora is different.
אלא הכא ela hacha by an אשם מצורע asham metzora לא מוקמי
ליה במילתיה lo mukmi lei bemilsai if you don't retain its distinctive
identity continue to call it an אשם מצורע asham metzora so אשם
נדבה מי איכא? asham nedava mi ika? There's no such thing as
a free will אשם. asham. You cannot have a generic אשם. asham.
Okay? So since you cannot have a generic אשם asham therefore it
has to be oh this is ראובן's Reuven אשם מצורע asham metzora
that's not going to count for him. Okay? So here we get
a great point about what happens when it's שלא לשמה. shelo lishma.
When it's שלא לשמה shelo lishma we've always known that it doesn't
count for the owner but it still operates. But here the question
is how does it operate? As generic עולה ola generic שלמים shelamim
or do we say no no no it's still you know like
your אשם מצורע asham metzora it's just not getting you out of
your obligation? And here it says well normally if it's an עולה
ola or שלמים shelamim it can become generic. If it's a חטאת
chatas שלא לשמה shelo lishma because it's not fulfilling an obligation a
חטאת chatas not fulfilling an obligation doesn't work at all. So the
only one that's where we've never really analyzed well enough is
the אשם asham and if you remember from זבחים Zevachim there
was
a
lot of reason like yeah the אשם asham should just be like
a חטאת chatas if it's not working to you know for effect
you for כפרה kapara then how does it still be what does
it work? So here the גמרא Gemara is struggling with that and
saying actually what we'll have to say by an אשם asham is
since you can't have generic אשם asham you have to be it's
your אשם asham and it makes sense because you're a מצורע. metzora.
מצורע, Metzora, you're a נזיר, Nazir, you did the sin, it's your
אשם, Asham, so it can still be work because it's not just
generic אשם, Asham, but it's not enough to get you out of
your obligation. So it's like, it's enough yours that it can be,
you can be מקריב makriv it because you can't just be מקריב
makriv generic אשם, Asham, but it's not enough, it's not done correctly
so you don't get out of your obligation. So since אשם Asham
retains its distinctive identity, it says yes, an אשם Asham of a
מצורע Metzora that gets a מנחה Mincha would retain the מנחה Mincha
if it was שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and without that it would
be invalid. The גמרא Gemara said about a חטאת Chatat though. Well,
you being, you mean why not say that it works but you
don't fulfill your
obligation? So the גמרא Gemara actually says, learns specifically a פסוק pasuk
from the חטאת. Chatat. But yeah, the חטאת's Chatat logic should be
that if it's, you know, you're right, in theory you could say,
well, it's for my sin, it just doesn't achieve כפרה. kappara. But
it's enough for my sin that it's not meaningless to bring, which
is essentially what we're saying here by the אשם. Asham. So yeah,
the גמרא Gemara just learns it out from a פסוק, pasuk, but
the question really becomes what's the logic to distinguish between an אשם
Asham and a חטאת? Chatat? And the גמרא Gemara never really gives
a good answer to that. I mean actually there was a very
graphic scene in the beginning of זבחים Zevachim where it says ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish fell on his stomach in the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash like, you know, and couldn't deal with this question about why
is an אשם Asham different than a... there is חטאת, Chatat, there
is a תנא tanna that says it is no different, but the
גמרא Gemara does not really have a
good
answer.
Yeah, birds or animals?
What? אשם? Asham? Yeah, it's a what? It's an animal, yeah. It's
not a bird. So what if... no, מצורע Metzora brings bird but
not for his אשם. Asham. His אשם Asham is a... he has
to bring an אשם? Asham? Yeah, an אשם.
Asham. What if he can't afford it?
No, the תורה Torah says if he can't afford it, he brings
birds for the חטאת Chatat and the עולה, Olah, but the lamb
still has to be an אשם. Asham. I mean, would the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash
have like a, like you know, like a, like a free loan
society or some type of... it might. מצורע Metzora is an illness
though.
I understand. I understand. So the תורה Torah does make
it easier, but yes,
one thing has actually to be a lamb. Were there be some
communal funds for people that couldn't even afford that? There could be,
I don't know, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't say. So what we're
all saying essentially is that with the other
one, the first position, whoever it was, was אביי.
Abaye. Abaye, it was Abaye.
Abaye was that everything remains has its distinctive identity and you're just
not יוצא.
yotzei. Right, and רבא's Rava saying
that this is, yes, this is still your, your עולה Olah for,
for the עומר. Omer. This is still the תמיד.
Tamid. It's just a תמיד Tamid that you're not יוצא. yotzei. It's
the עולה Olah for the עומר, Omer, you're not יוצא, yotzei, but
it still has all the requirements that go with a תמיד Tamid
or that go with the עולה Olah of an עומר. Omer. Right,
so רבא's Rava saying that for the other ones... no, they just
become generic עולה Olah and therefore you just do your regular עולה
Olah ונסכיה u-nesacheha and nothing special. But, but in contradistinction to the
מצורע Metzora where you do do these special מנחות minchos because it's
an אשם Asham and because an אשם, Asham, you can't bring a
generic אשם. Asham. The only way you can bring an אשם Asham
is if it retains some of its identity. Okay, so again, this
was a great discussion. I wish we had it in זבחים. Zevachim.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says: תניא נמי הכי. Tanya nami
hachi. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. Tanya kevaseih de-Rabbi Yochanan. We taught like
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan this idea that it still has, it still
has its requirements. Let's take a look. אשם מצורע ששחטו שלא לשמו.
Asham Metzora she-shechato shelo lishmo. You slaughtered the אשם מצורע שלא לשמו.
Asham Metzora shelo lishmo. או שלא נתן מדמו על גבי בהונות. O
shelo nasan mi-damo al gabi behonos. Or you did not put it
on the, the blood on the ears of the מצורע. Metzora. So
therefore וכו׳ v'chu you're not יוצא yotzei it as an אשם מצורע.
Asham Metzora. Nevertheless, הרי זה עולה לגבי מזבח. harei zeh oleh legabi
mizbeach. You put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. וטעון נסכים, v'taun nesachim,
and you need the נסכים, nesachim, meaning the מנחה mincha that comes
with it, וצריך אשם אחר להתירו. v'tzarich Asham acher lehatiro. But you
need another אשם. Asham. So it still has, so the one hand,
if you had just bracketed out the issue of שלא נתן מדמו
על גבי המצורע, shelo nasan mi-damo al gabi ha-Metzora, that you would
have understood. That you would basically say, okay, it's a hundred percent
my, as it would, my obligation of an אשם Asham and it's
a full אשם מצורע. Asham Metzora. It's just I didn't use it
for the ritual of being מטהר metaher the מצורע. Metzora. So the
טהרה tahara didn't happen, but the קרבן korban happened. That in a
sense makes a nice, makes a lot of sense. It's fully an
אשם Asham of a מצורע. Metzora. You fully bring, bring it the
normal way, but I need another thing cause I didn't use it
for the טהרה tahara process. So the חידוש chiddush is that he
also sticks in in that ברייתא שלא לשמו. braisa shelo lishmo. And
that's what it's saying that even שלא לשמו shelo lishmo has the
same effect, that it's fully
an אשם Asham of a מצורע, Metzora, you're just not יוצא. yotzei.
Except as opposed to just saying the first way, which is you
didn't get achieve טהרה, tahara, here it's saying you're not even יוצא
yotzei your קרבן korban obligation, but it still has the identity of
the אשם מצורע Asham Metzora and you still do it the normal
way. Alright, so that is very interesting in terms of an אשם
שלא לשמו Asham shelo lishmo retains its identity or its distinctive identity
more than other קרבנות. korbanos. It needs to, or else you couldn't
be מקריב makriv it. Alright, now we go to the next משנה.
Mishnah. We
go back
to
the measuring things. כל מדות שבמקדש היו נגדשות חוץ משל כהן גדול
שהיו גודש לתוכה. Kol midos she-ba-mikdash hayu nigdashos chutz mi-shel Kohen Gadol
she-hayu godesh le-sochah. So this is basically רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir as
the גמרא Gemara will explain. If you remember רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says that there were two dry measures in the מקדש Mikdash for
the עשרון, issaron, one that you would heap and one that you
would level. So there and this is basically saying, so all of
the מדות midos in the מקדש Mikdash you would heap, except for
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the חביתין chavitin which you would level.
And רש"י Rashi can
explain
the reason, use it like that
if
you have to divide it in two and pour it into two
separate vessels, you don't want heaping cause then some is going to
spill. מידה, Midah, so it's heapingness is on... inside, which means it's
not heaped over the edge. Now, now we're going to turn to
the question about which we came up in the גמרא Gemara about
whether when stuff goes beyond the lip, the upper
lip, does it get the קדושה, Kedusha,
is it sanctified by the vessel itself? So let's take a look.
מדת הלח, Midat Halach, if you're dealing with a liquid measure,
בירוציהן קדוש. Beyrotzayan Kadosh. So there, the amount that exceeds over, which
I was correct, called the meniscus. Yes, I saw your spot.
Okay, anyway, so that is קודש, Kodesh, that
is sanctified by the vessel. ומדת היבש Umidat Hayavesh בירוציהן, Beyrotzayan, whoa,
nice חברה Chevre today, ומדת היבש Umidat Hayavesh בירוציהן חול. Beyrotzayan Chol.
But dry measures, the amount that exceeds over is not sanctified. Very
bizarre, why should it be different? Although one thing to think about
very clearly is, yes, is that there is a difference is that,
you know, is that by the liquid measure it really, first of
all, there's not as much that overflows, and not only
is it not as much, but it's adhering to the vessel, right?
You know, it only works because of surface tension. So it's really
connected to the vessel, the amount that's overflowing. It needs the vessel
in a sense to retain to stay there.
Whereas when you overflow, the stuff on
the top doesn't need the vessel, right? It's really just, you know,
it has a pile, so if you think I piled something into
a box and then I go more, that's sitting on top of
the pile that is underneath, it doesn't really, you know, it doesn't
really need
the vessel to keep it where it is. By the way, which
is another reason to think about the difference between, you know, the
generalist things that has come up before in the גמרא, Gemara, it's
actually going to come up right now in the משנה, Mishna, is
that liquid measures might have, might be כלי שרת Klei Shares and
dry measures not. And we've never really, you know, that idea's come
up, it's going to come up right now in the משנה, Mishna,
we've never discussed why that's the case. Now this משנה Mishna is
going to discuss why, it's just going to discuss whether. But one
thing to think about is the same idea. What's the basic definition
of a liquid? The basic definition of a liquid, anybody is takes
the shape of its container.
So a, by
very definition, a liquid measure really holds the liquid, you know, in
a way that a dry measure does not. A dry measure measures
the liquid, but the stuff would be there with or without the
measure, it's not the shape, it's not the volume. No, no, no,
if I took away the vessel, the liquid would spill out, right?
If I took away the box that
the stuff is in,
it
could very well retain its shape. As flour, that's true, that
is true, that is true, that is true. All right, so okay,
so it would just ball. I know about flour. I still think,
I still think that as a general rule, a liquid measure more
is seen as, you know, affecting and holding, alright, holding the liquid
in a way that a dry measure does not to the same
degree. It keeps liquid. Right, exactly. Anyway, I just put that out
there as something to
think about, why liquid measures might be כלי שרת Klei Shares because,
you know, the degree to which we say they define the identity
of what's in it, I could see that more by liquid than
by solid. But anyway, here we're not talking about that, here we're
talking about the excess. So you say the excess certainly that could
be true, that the excess liquid is much more requires the vessel
than the excess solid. Anyway, that's the distinction here, that's just my
hypothesis. But it says that that's the distinction between liquid and dry.
That's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kama. Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees
to this, but he gives an explanation. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
the excess which is not so defined by the but it needs,
it's not defined by the vessel, but needs the vessel in a
way, yeah, in a way that the solid does not. רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva gives another explanation, but in
a way his explanation begs an explanation. רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva
Omer מדת הלח קודש Midat Halach Kodesh לפיכך בירוציהן קודש. Lefikach Beyrotzayan
Kodesh. Here's the reason: it's not a difference about the excess, it's
a difference about the very vessel itself. Liquid vessels are קודש, Kodesh,
are כלי שרת, Klei Shares, are sanctified, and therefore not only the
liquid in them and the liquid above them becomes sanctified. מדת היבש
חול, Midat Hayavesh Chol, dry measures are not sanctified, are not כלי
שרת, Klei Shares, לפיכך בירוציהן חול. Lefikach Beyrotzayan Chol. Therefore the excess
is not sanctified, but it's not just the excess, it's what's in
them as well as not sanctified. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva basically
says yeah, there's a difference between dry and liquid, but it's not
about the excess, it's about the very thing itself that, therefore, you
know,
that dry measures were not כלי שרת Klei Shares and did not
sanctify. Now of course you'll say, so how did you wind up
using it if it's not sanctified? So the answer is because then
eventually you mix it with the oil and therefore, which was sanctified,
and you mix it also in a liquid vessel when you're mixing
it with the oil and it becomes sanctified when it turns into
dough. But it does not become sanctified as flour, that's what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. Is he
trying to explain
him?
Yes, but he's explaining, but he goes further, because he basically says
that not only the excess wasn't sanctified, even the flour in the
vessel
wasn't sanctified, it only becomes sanctified when it is later put into
a liquid vessel, a liquid, you know. a liquid measure when it's
mixed with the oil. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, but
until that point it's not sanctified at all. Or until the second
because you're using whatever the process that sanctifies the vessel which allows
the vessel—ah, so that is, that's a good question. That would be
the כלי שרת k'lei shares
were sanctified by שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. After there was no longer
שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha, as long as there was שמן המשחה shemen
hamishcha they were sanctified. After that it says עבודתן מחנכתן, avodasan mechanechasan,
so the first time they were used they were sanctified verbally and
then the first time they were put to use at the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash they became sanctified. But why couldn't one fashion a
way to do that to a solid? Yeah, so that's the funny
thing. It never says that it couldn't be done. It just sort
of says it as a matter of fact. Oh, the solid ones
weren't sanctified. And it's never clear why not. So I gave you
a certain conceptual explanation that maybe is which really saying that maybe
they are כלי שרת k'lei shares but they don't define what's in
it rather than saying that they're not a כלי שרת. k'lei shares.
I acknowledge that. It could also be maybe there's a practical issue
although I haven't thought this through. Maybe somebody wants to come to
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, measure out their flour, then take it
home and make their מנחה mincha or something like that. Maybe in
a way you wouldn't do with the oil because the quantity of
oil would be a lot less. But I haven't really thought that
through and it's not exactly clear to me why that should be
a major difference between solid and liquid. So again, it's not it
never explains what the basis of that difference is. Now, so that's
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and now you have so he's explaining but
actually going further than the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. And now you
have yet another opinion. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says לא מן השם זה lo min hasheim zeh or
לא מן השם הוא זה, lo min hasheim hu zeh, that's not
the reason, or לא משום זה, lo mishum zeh, אלא שלח נעקר
והיבש אינו נעקר. ela shelach ne'ekar vehayavesh eino ne'ekar. When you pour
liquid in a vessel, it's not that the new liquid is what's
on top and the old liquid is on the bottom. Right? If
you're pouring liquid in a vessel, right, the new stuff goes in
and pushes the stuff in to the top. Right? Imagine you're pouring.
If I'm pouring a cup of orange juice or whatever I'm pouring,
right, is it the new orange juice that's staying on top? Maybe
if I'm pouring oil that's true, but I'm pouring orange juice, it's
piercing down and it's pushing stuff up. So he says the stuff
on the top of the vessel was already sanctified in the vessel,
so you don't need to explain why. So there yes, the overage
is sanctified because it was in the vessel itself, whereas the dry,
the stuff on the top never got in the vessel and therefore
is not sanctified. That's a nice explanation. Right? Yes. Which you just
mentioned, maybe the difference between לח lach and יבש yavesh in terms
of the כלים keilim is that if if you assume, we've gone
through reasons to assume this, so if you assume that the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash had the gold standard measure, right? So the only
way to to make a new a copy of a liquid measure
is to pour from one to the other, right? I mean, you're
not going to measure exactly the dimensions, but a solid measure by
something by weight, you put it on the scale and then you
don't have to exactly copy. I don't understand why is that different
liquid and solid? Why can't you do the same thing? Because you
have to use the actual כלי שרת k'lei shares to measure the
the non-כלי שרת k'lei shares to verify its dimension. Okay. Whereas a
solid like a weight well but a solid is a volume, they
both volume measures, and if you convert them to weight by a
constant type of a by constant thing that you're measuring, you could
do it either way, but they're both volume measures. Okay, alright so
let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. So מאני, mani, who's our משנה
Mishna
that distinguishes between whether things were measured leveled or measured heaping? אי
רבי מאיר חד גדוש הוי, ee Rabbi Meir chad gadush havei, if
it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, now this goes to your gold standard
question, because if רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
that
there was one heaping measure and one flat measure and this משנה
Mishna says all
of the measures were heaping, sounds like there were multiple measuring vessels.
So here actually the גמרא Gemara makes it sound that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir did not just mean there were two types but he
actually made it sound like you were suggesting Dov that there was
actually just one vessel
that was the measuring vessel. So why does our משנה Mishna say
all of the measuring vessels? אי רבנן, ee Rabbanan, and if it's
the rabbis, then there's no two different, חד ומחוק הוי, chad umachuk
havei, it was only one and it was leveled. So how does
what does our משנה Mishna mean when it says all of the
measuring vessels were heaping? So אמר רב חסדא לעולם רבי מאיר, amar
Rav Chisda le'olam Rabbi Meir, it is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, ומהי
כל מדות, umai kol midos, what does it mean all of the
measures? כל מדות, kol midos, all of the measurings were done with
heaping except for the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So even the answer,
Dov, and this goes back, it makes it sound like there was
only one vessel, it doesn't even want to say no he means
one type. It says like yes there was one vessel but it
was all done every time you used it all the measurings you
did with it were heaping. Although that is a little bit far,
that seems to be I gotta tell you practically very unfeasible to
think.
So the maybe the way I would just read it is is
that maybe מדות midos still means one type of vessel
but the גמרא's Gemara bothered
that there was still only it was only used for an עשרון
issaron and maybe it sounds maybe the גמרא Gemara made it sound
like all of the vessels made it sound like there were different
you would measure different amounts. But the simple read of the גמרא
Gemara is like you were saying
that there was just one vessel which is I admit gotta be
pretty inefficient if a lot of people are bringing מנחות minchos and
especially if you think about
it that's not just about bringing a מנחה mincha but it's about...
it's hard to imagine
that they only had one vessel to use. What? And the cleaning
of it, because if you have something dry, it leaves residue. That's
a good point. For something for the next thing. Although, you know,
no reason
that if you assume a certain מחילה mechila or whatever you couldn't
use the other person's flour as well, but that's an interesting question,
whether they had bothered cleaning it out. But okay, it's a good
point too. Yes? I kind of see this as a metaphor for
Adam and Eve. That Adam wasn't complete until Eve was created, and
the dry didn't become sanctified until they joined. Oh, very nice.
The whole yin and yang thing going on here. All right, very
nice. Now, the other thing I would just say about this by
the way that's not clear in the משנה Mishnah is this משנה
Mishnah seems to be a little contradictory. The משנה Mishnah says, and
this is a question
we asked before and I have not yet
found מפרשים meforshim that really deal with this head-on. The משנה Mishnah
says
that the dry measures they would measure heaping, and then what's the
very next line of the משנה? Mishnah? That the overage of the
dry measures was not sanctified. So how do you measure it heaping
and it's not sanctified? So it could just be the assumption is,
okay, it's not sanctified at this moment, it gets sanctified when you
transfer it to a liquid vessel and you add the oil and
so on. Maybe, I mean in general you have to deal with
that problem, if it's not sanctified what do you do with the
overage? Presumably you don't get rid of it, you still have the
overage, so it gets sanctified at the next step. But it's a
little, it's a little ironic that the beginning of the משנה Mishnah
says they would measure everything with an overage, all the dry measures,
and then
says, "Oh,
but it wasn't sanctified."
Is there any concept equivalent to
ביטול bittul with regards to sanctified and not sanctified?
That is once something not sanctified comes into contact with something sanctified
it overwhelmingly overwhelms it?
Yeah, that's a good point.
There is that idea, yes, when you have a mixture you have
to treat it like the more stringent, and even in ways that's
even more that's even more, you know, that's actually based on a
פסוק pasuk in the תורה, Torah, וכל אשר יגע בבשרה יקדש, vechol
asher yiga bivesarah yikdash, by a חטאת, chatas, by the מנחה, mincha,
and the גמרא Gemara learns out in חולין Chullin even in ways
in which by normal things
it would be ביטול, bittul, by קדשים kodshim there isn't ביטול, bittul,
and therefore yes, you have to treat it like- but it does
not make it sanctified like, oh now I can use it for
my קרבן, korban, it's always just the stringencies.
You know, now I can't eat it at the wrong time and
I can't
take it out of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and so on,
that does apply.
Okay, by the way, I should say that the issue also here
is when it says sanctified or not, do we mean absolute or
do we mean degree? You know, it could very well be based
on other גמרות Gemaras it sounds like that yes, I would sanctify
my flour, this flour I'm going to use for the מנחה, mincha,
but when I sanctify it verbally it doesn't yet have קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, which means I can redeem it if it stays overnight
or I can take it out of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
I mean I sanctified it at home outside the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. So the sanctity of the vessel, it gives it a קדושת
הגוף, kedushat haguf, a more of an intrinsic sanctity. Then if I
take it out of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash I invalidate it,
if it stays overnight it becomes invalid, that's the type of sanctity
we're talking about here, and I can no longer redeem it once
it's sanctified. So we're talking about the higher level, yes. That kind
of קדושה kedusha as a concept sounds a lot like the idea
of possession, that is you could in contract transfer something by agreement
but in fact you don't own it until you hold it, so
perhaps the same here. Perhaps the overage is not held by the
actual possessory object. Well, that's interesting. As I've been defining saying until
now, actually there are two concepts to קדושה. kedusha. One is ownership
by the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, which is actually not קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, it's more like if I dedicate, donate my car to
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash they own it, but they own it
as property, not in terms of its, you know, how it's going
to be used and it's going to serve sanctified ends. It's just
owned, okay? That's really, that's more קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, not קדושת
הגוף, kedushat haguf, and that could be when I sanctify the flour.
The next step is called קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, which much more
has to do with its purpose and how it's going to be
used and what its goals are. So when I sanctify my animal
for a קרבן, korban, not to just donate it to the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, that's a type of a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf.
It's going to be used itself and it's directed towards, you know,
this type of purpose. So it could very well be that that
is exactly the shift that goes from when I verbally sanctify the
flour to when I put it in the vessel, and that's why
I was talking about the idea of a vessel is sort of
like not owning, but holding in a way that transforms its identity,
that defines its identity. I think it's more about identity than it
is about ownership. I think ownership is the first stage. Okay, so
now yes, it means it was only קדושת דמים kedushat damim when
it's in this כלי שרת? kli sharet? What? So it means only
קדושת דמים kedushat damim when it's in this כלי- kli no, before
the כלי שרת. kli sharet. כלי שרת kli sharet gives it a
קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. That's the whole point. But then that's the
shift. Before it, when it's קדושת פה, kedushat peh, it's not קדושת
הגוף, kedushat haguf, it's like a קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. It's more
of an it's owned by the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, but it
can be redeemed. But it doesn't answer why the בירוץ beirutz is
not- no no no, that I'm not dealing with. I'm just dealing
with the conceptual change from the verbal sanctity to the כלי שרת.
kli sharet. Okay, מדת הלח היו קודש, midat halach hayu kodesh, so
now we're dealing with the liquid thing, the overage is קודש. kodesh.
So, במאי קמיפלגי... bemai kamiflegi... what's this debate of the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi?
It seems, was it רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? We see, yeah, we
have a three-way debate. So תנא קמא סבר מידת הלח נמשחה בין
מבפנים בין מבחוץ, Tanna Kamma savar midas halach nimshacha bein mibifnim bein
mibachutz, here you do here you see about how the כלי שרת
klei shares are sanctified through anointing. So when the liquid measures were
sanctified, they were anointed inside and out. So all of it, all
surfaces were considered כלי שרת. klei shares. מידת... Now why is it
important on the out? Because the assumption here is that the way
the overage is sanctified is through the is through the lip. Now,
it's a little bit bizarre. I mean, it actually works for liquids
more than solids, right? Because if it's being held, the meniscus on
the top, right, it's held, it's adhering to the lip, so it
not to the inner not to the inner part, you know, but
to the actual lip here, which is the outside. So it assumes
that in order to sanctify the overage, it's coming through the lip,
and that's only if the outside were was sanctified. Now, that does
not work for dry. But it doesn't work for dry. For liquid
either as much. It does work for liquid. Liquid you need the
surface tension. Yeah, but what about the stuff right on the middle
on the top? That's not really adhering. No, but that's held from
the surface tension that starts here, no? No, it doesn't start from
the top. I don't think so. It starts at the sides. I
think so, no? The way it works is that the molecules the
molecules have a constant attraction to things around them. And so if
there's nothing above them, then there's an added attraction to what's below
and to the side. Aha. So you think it's actually adhering to
what's below, it's not about adhering to the lip. Yeah, but of
course, I don't know if they really understood that way. All right,
I don't know, but it certainly doesn't work for dry. I mean,
for dry you could have a box that
has no lip and you could still put stuff on top. So
I don't get it exactly.
I mean, liquid maybe, I don't get it for the dry. Anyway,
so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma.
holds that the liquid ones, the outside was also sanctified, which includes
the lip, and therefore the overage was sanctified. מידת יבש נמשחה מבפנים
ולא נמשחה מבחוץ. midas yavesh nimshacha mibifnim velo nimshacha mibachutz.
The dry ones were sanctified on the inside, not the outside. So
therefore, there's no way to sanctify that the overage gets sanctified. That's
the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma, רבי עקיבא סבר מידת הלח נמשחה בין
מבפנים בין מבחוץ. Rabbi Akiva savar midas halach nimshacha bein mibifnim bein
mibachutz. There he agrees with the תנא קמא,
that the liquid ones were inside and out. So because it's out,
it can sanctify the overage. מידת היבש לא נמשחה כל עיקר, midas
hayavesh lo nimshacha kol ikar, were not sanctified at all. The dry
ones he basically holds were not כלי שרת. klei shares. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds that the dry measures, not just the overage
wasn't sanctified, nothing was sanctified. And as I said, the sanctity would
probably occur when it got mixed with the liquid and was put
in a type of a liquid vessel, but
he holds the dry ones were not sanctified at all.
So it wasn't just the overage.
Yes, first you then Bobby.
Yeah, I just have another way to explain that outside versus inside.
Any the the overage is technically outside of the כלי. kli. Oh,
so conceptually if you're sanctifying the outside, it relates not just to
the outer wall, but to any concept of outside. In an earthenware
כלי, kli, anything inside is gets the טומאה tumah of the... Right,
right, right. That's an interesting point. I get the point. I get
the point. Once you're sanctifying the outside, then conceptually
it means the outside of the כלי kli is sanctified, not just
the outer wall. That's a nice idea. So it's not actually the
lip, it's the concept of the outer part of the כלי. kli.
That's a nice idea. Bobby. So if you can going back to
what we were saying before. All right, because I think it's important.
Yeah. If you're using the same vessel, let's say you use this
כלי kli for the oil, now
you're going to use the same vessel that you've sanctified for dry
measure. It becomes unsanctified because...
No, no, no, you're not going to use they that's why the
previous משנה Mishnah said you had separate measuring vessels. They were very
separate they were defined very, yes, defined separately. And the point being,
though, you would use when you made the flour, you would actually
do it in a vessel that was made for liquid so that
that sanctified... not the flour, when you made the dough, excuse me,
you would do it in a liquid vessel. Right. Okay, so that's
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that the dry ones were not at all.
רבי יוסי סבר אידי ואידי נמשחה מבפנים ולא נמשחה מבחוץ. Rabbi Yossi
savar idi ve'idi nimshacha mibifnim velo nimshacha mibachutz. Both were on the
inside, not the outside, so they do not sanctify what is outside
of them. I very much like that explanation. והכא ve-hacha so why
then does the liquid one, the overage sanctify? והכא היינו טעמא דלח
נעקר, ve-hacha hainu taama delach ne'ekar, because the liquid is uprooted from
where it was. ומגו דמנא קאתי, umigo demana ka'ati, and it's coming
from within the vessel, so the top on the top would used
to be on the bottom. והיבש אינו נעקר, vehayavesh eino ne'ekar, and
not by the dry, which is a very nice explanation. So now
the גמרא Gemara has a question. וכי נעקר מאי הוי, ve-chi ne'ekar
mai havei, who cares that it was uprooted and it originally was
in the vessel? What? Displaced? Thank you, that is an excellent word,
right? I was being a little literal, but you are right, displaced.
Okay. So who cares that it was displaced? גברא למאי דצריך קא
מחבב. gavra lemai detzarich ka mechabiv. If you are if there's an
overage, when I am pouring my oil into this vessel, I'm only
trying to sanctify a לוג. log. I'm not trying to sanctify a
לוג log and a bit. So even if it touched the inner
vessel, the question is this is really not limited to the last
position, it's that if the vessel, if we're assuming that the measure
is precise, right, not that it includes the overage, but the amount,
let's say the לוג Log is precise, why should the overage ever
be sanctified? I never, I only want to sanctify a לוג, Log,
I don't want to sanctify more than a לוג, Log, so why
should we ever sanctify more than I want to? So that's the
גמרא Gemorah's question, which really applies to anyone who says the overage
is sanctified. So אמר רב דימי בר שישנא משמיה דרב, Amar Rav
Dimi bar Shishna mishmeih deRav, זאת אומרת, zos omeres, this teaches you
כלי שרת מקדשין שלא מדעת, klei shares mekadeshin shelo mada'as, that the
power of כלי שרת klei shares is that they sanctify even if
it's not your intention. Now again, it's not starting from nothing, first
you had a verbal sanctification and then you put in the כלי
שרת, klei shares, but at least in that context, what it actualizes
it or the circumstances define it and it does not require at
that stage your intention. So you're right, that is why the overage
is sanctified.
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says לעולם אימא לך כלי שרת
אין מקדשין אלא מדעת. leolam eima lach klei shares ein mekadeshin ella
mada'as. No, I will tell you that it really does not work
if it's not your intention. גזירה שמא יאמרו מוציאין מכלי שרת לחול.
Gezeirah shema yomru motzi'in miklei shares lechol. And really our entire משנה,
Mishnah, this is very disappointing cause it turns our entire משנה Mishnah
into a דרבנן. DeRabbanan. Basically it's saying you're right, overage is never
sanctified cause it only works, it would never be more than your
intention. So when the משנה Mishnah discusses it being sanctified and what's
one of the most immediate relevances of it having קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguf is that you can't redeem it, you can't sort of exchange
it for something else. So that's a דרבנן DeRabbanan concern, if people
see that you're redeeming the overage they'll say oh, כלי שרת klei
shares you can redeem stuff even that was in a כלי שרת.
kli shares. So our entire משנה Mishnah is no longer מעיקר הדין,
me'ikar hadin, it's only a דרבנן. DeRabbanan. It's much better to read
it the other way which is forget what you're thinking, the כלי
שרת klei shares are operating based on their own power. Yes.
Does that mean that we're using something that is חולין chullin at
a biblical level for an עבודה? avodah?
That is,
well, that's a good question. You mean your point is that if
it was sanctified not just in terms of the restrictions but now
I'm going to put it into my מנחה? minchah?
Yeah, I don't know, I guess my answer would be that it
can't be any different than the story with the flour. If the
flour wasn't sanctified how do you use it and the answer is
well when you eventually mix it all together you're mixing it in
a vessel that's going to sanctify it.
So you've got non-sanctified flour being mixed with partially non-sanctified oil.
You're right, it's pretty funny. You're right, but the most relevant issues
are what do you do with them before you've, you know, can
you redeem them, do they become פסול? posul? But once you actually
make the dough in a vessel that's a כלי שרת kli shares
then it ends it right there. But I guess the נפקא מינה
nafka mina would be for the wine because if you measured out
the wine in this vessel and then you poured it on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, so you're doing, yeah, that's a very good question, it's
a, yeah, yeah, it's a very, very good question, yeah.
How can you be sanctified בעל כרחו, be'al korcho, you're sanctifying the
whole thing? You may say I only want the לוג, log, but
presumably you know you're putting more than that.
Right, I mean the גמרא Gemorah could, there were other answers available
to the גמרא Gemorah like, you know, you're not, you don't think
so precisely, you know, you're whatever, you maybe you're thinking whatever's in
the כלי שרת kli shares
should be sanctified, the amount
necessarily, so it's funny that the גמרא Gemorah was so bothered with
it. And it's also very disappointing that the answer, or at least
this answer, not the first answer, it turns our whole משנה Mishnah
into a דרבנן DeRabbanan issue. And I think that the point also
about does that mean that you might even wind up using non-sanctified
material was a good one.
Okay, so let's see what, so let's see where the גמרא Gemorah
goes. גמרא Gemorah's going to challenge this whole idea of גזירה gezeirah
anyway. So מתיב רב זירא, moseiv Rav Zeira, or רב זירא Rabbi
Zeira asked on this, סידר את הלחם ואת הבזיכין לאחר השבת, sidder
es halechem v'es habezichin l'achar hashabas, let's say you put, this is
a ברייתא, Braisa, you put the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim on the
שולחן shulchan but you put it up on Sunday. Somehow you missed
putting it up on שבת, Shabbos, so you put the bread with
the, you know, sort of dishes of the frankincense on the table
on Sunday. והקטיר את הבזיכין משבת, Vehiktir es habezichin m'shabbos, then the
following שבת Shabbos you like you normally do on שבת Shabbos you
offered up the frankincense, פסולה, Psulah, the bread is not valid, why?
Because the whole idea of the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim is you
put it up from שבת Shabbos to שבת, Shabbos, so its time
to be offered is only a week from the day that it
was placed. So therefore since it was placed on Sunday it cannot
be offered on שבת, Shabbos, it's like מחוסר זמן, mechusar zman, it's
almost like the infant animal that's not a week old, so that's
sort of the conceptually how it is, it's not yet the right
time to offer it, it has to be a week from the
time it was placed. So it's invalid. So what does the ברייתא
Braisa say you should do? So כיצד יעשה, keitzad ya'aseh, what do
you do to offer up such bread? יניחנו לשבת הבאה, Yanihennu l'shabbos
haba'ah, don't wait, don't do it Sunday, then you'll always be off,
so wait till the next שבת Shabbos and then you'll offer it
up next שבת, Shabbos, and then it'll have been on the table
for a week. שאפילו היה על השולחן ימים רבים אין בכך כלום,
She'afillu hayah al hashulchan yamim rabim ein be'kach klum, even if it
was on the שולחן shulchan for a long time, more than a
week, it does not become פסול. posul. Why does it not become
פסול posul בלינה? belinah? It does not become פסול posul בלינה, belinah,
right, because the question is if the bread was supposed to be
offered up on the seventh day and you didn't offer it, why
doesn't it become invalid for sleeping over? So the answer is is
that because well because it really didn't become sanctified when you put
it on on Sunday, Sunday was the wrong time. so it's really
only going to be sanctified when it comes שבת Shabbos and then
it's going to be כשר kasher for the next שבת. Shabbos. However,
this by the way, that's one way of understanding it, that's based
on another גמרא. Gemara. The simple sense of this ברייתא, braisa, though,
makes it sound like there's something special about the שולחן, Shulchan, maybe
because the whole idea of the שולחן Shulchan is to hold the
bread for seven days and not to offer up on the same
day, that when it's on the שולחן Shulchan it does not become
invalid with לינה. linah. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to
have a question about a גזירה, gezeirah, if you're afraid about what
people are going to see and say, they're going to say that
it's not just about the שולחן Shulchan or it's not special because
it was put there at the wrong time and they'll say any
time something's in a כלי שרת, kli shares, it never becomes פסול
pasul בלינה belinah because the same way this stuff, I kept it
on for like eleven days or whatever thirteen days. So why aren't
we concerned about what people will say? So it says ואמאי, ve'amai,
why are we let you do that? התם נמי לימא, hatam nami
leima, well let's say גזירה שמא יאמרו, gezeirah shema yomru, מפקידים בכלי
שרת, mafkidim bikli shares, that you can store things in a כלי
שרת kli shares and if it's on a כלי שרת, kli shares,
it doesn't become פסול pasul like the stuff on the bread on
the table doesn't become פסול. pasul. So why aren't we concerned about
appearance? So the גמרא Gemara says פנימה חוץ קא רמית, penimah chutz
ka ramit, you're asking from inside to outside? פנים לאו כולי עלמא
ידעי, panim lav kulei alma yadei, inside where there's the שולחן, Shulchan,
who goes into the inner part? יהוכא הני מילי, yehucha hanei milei,
it's not public knowledge what's going on there, so we're not afraid
about what people will say. חוץ, chutz, on the outside, כולי עלמא
ידעי, kulei alma yadei, everybody knows, everybody knows that you're using the
little overage of your oil vessel and therefore we're afraid of what
it will lead to. So again, a very non-satisfying answer about a
concern about appearances. It's clearly the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah
is that it really is sanctified and yes, either because כלי שרת
klei shares operate regardless of your intent or because your intent is
not that specific to exclude the overage. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
goes on. תנן התם, tnan hatam, מותר נסכים לקיץ המזבח. motar nesachim
lekayitz hamizbeach. The leftover liquid liquids are used for the summer
of the altar. קיץ kayitz actually can mean it could mean the
summer. It means the vacation of the altar. But it also means
like figs that are eaten. רש"י Rashi says it could mean like
figs, but it means something like the dessert of the altar. This
was a phrase that refers to when nothing is going on in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's a slow day in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so it's not respectful to see like, you know,
everybody's hanging around, not doing anything, it's like not operating, so you
would bring some sacrifices from communal funds to keep things moving, keep
things operating. And that was called קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. Now, where
did this money come to bring these עולות olos for keeping the
מזבח mizbeach operating? So it says, oh, the leftover נסכים nesachim were
effectively redeemed and the money of or sold and redeemed and that
money went to pay for these קרבנות. korbanos. So what are these
leftover נסכים? nesachim? So מאי מותר נסכים, mai motar nesachim, what? קיץ
המזבח.
kayitz hamizbeach.
Right. מאי מותר נסכים, mai motar nesachim, רבי חייא בר יוסף אמר
בירוצי מדות. Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef amar beirutei midot. It was the
overage. Now, how much overage there is in that little meniscus that
goes, I don't know, but the other question is, I thought I
was telling you, weren't say Rabbi Linzer didn't you just say the
whole idea of קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf is that you can't redeem
it? Right. So תוספות Tosafot says, okay, but we'll have to say
that that, you know, that if you look at this תוספות, Tosafot,
בירוצי מדות beirutei midot אע"ג דנתקדשו, af al gav denitkadshu,
לוקחים מהם כבשים לקיץ המזבח כדתניא בראש פרקין דלב בית דין מתנה
עליהם. lokchim mehem kvasim lekayitz hamizbeach kedisanya bereish pirkin delav beis din
matneh aleihem. So because it was for communal purposes, בית דין Beis
Din stipulated that they should be able to redeem it in order
to, you know, keep those funds in order to use it to
pay for this. Of course, if that's true, then, you know, one
of the major implications of it being sanctified has now been curtailed.
So that is
what רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
no, no, no, that's not what we're talking about, here's what we're
talking about, anyway, how much would that be? Here's what we're talking
about about the leftover funds. We're talking כאותה ששנינו ke'ota sheshaninu what
we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, המקבל עליו לספק סלתות מארבע ועמדו
בשלוש. hamikabel alav lesapek selatot me'arba ve'amdu beshalosh. So here again we're
talking we're talking about the business that surrounds the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Okay, so somebody basically makes a contract with the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, I will provide your flour for your needs at the
at the rate of, you know, four סאה se'ah per whatever per
maneh or whatever it would be. ארבע סאה arba se'ah for every,
you know, hundred dollars or ten dollars. ועמדו בשלוש, ve'amdu beshalosh, and
then the flour got more expensive. So now it really costs it's
really the rate is really ten dollars for שלוש סאה, shalosh se'ah,
not four. But I contracted for four. So here's a lesson of
never do business with the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they always have
the upper hand. So it says יספק מארבע. yesapek me'arba. So I
still have to provide at the rate of four because it's with
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so they always have the upper hand.
I mean, I on the one hand I assume it's a very
high volume business, but these are some of the consequences that you
if things change, they always have the upper hand. משלוש ועמדו מארבע,
mishalosh ve'amdu me'arba, if I contracted to provide שלוש סאה shalosh se'ah
per whatever ten dollars and now it's ארבע סאה, arba se'ah, so
maybe I can oh, now make in a nice profit, no. יספק
מארבע, yesapek me'arba, now I have to give them the better rate
and I have to provide at the rate of four. Okay, anyway...
שיד הקדש על העליונה sheyad hekdesh al haelyona that the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash always has the upper hand. Now, if בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash always has the upper hand, so they contracted to get three
סאה se'ah per whatever, you know, for ten dollars, and now they're
getting four סאה, se'ah, they're getting extra. So if they're getting extra,
what do they do with all this extra wheat, that flour that
they're getting for their money? They'll resell it and use the proceeds
to pay for the קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. So when they make
a profit because they always get the upper hand, they can use
the overage to pay for the קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. So that's
what he says. Now it's interesting, by the way, that that's not
נסכים nesachim according to him. According to him, that is, that's what
do you call it? That's not liquid, that's solid, that's flour. Now
you could say the same thing is true for flour, but we
also know that sometimes נסכים nesachim refers to not just the liquid,
the wine, but it refers to the מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, the
flour that came with the wine on the קרבן, korban, and that
presumably is what he is referring to. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on, תניא כוותיה tanya kvassei דרבי חייא בר יוסף, de-Rabbi
Chiya bar Yosef, תניא כוותיה tanya kvassei דרבי יוחנן, de-Rabbi Yochanan, we
have ברייתות braisas that support each position. תניא כוותיה tanya kvassei דרבי
חייא בר יוסף, de-Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef, ביוצאי מדת beyotzei middas הללו
halalu מה היו עושים בהם, mah hayu osin bahem, what would they
do with the overage of these vessels? Now, by the way, it
might also mean the dry overage even if they weren't, that actually
fits better, how they could redeem it. So you have the dry
overage, it's not sanctified, but what do you do with it? You
sell it and you make a profit. Okay, so מה היו עושים
בהם, mah hayu osin bahem, אם יש זבח אחר im yesh zevach
acher יקריבו עמו, yakrivu imo, if there's another sacrifice, use it for
that. ואם לנו ve'im lanu יפסלו
בלינה, yifsalu belinah, now here's where it sounds like we're talking about
the ones that were sanctified because number one, it's ready to be
used for another sacrifice. If it sleeps, if it spends the night,
it's invalidated. So all that means we're talking about an overage that
does have קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, and if
you cannot, and if you, you know, it's going to become פסול
pasul and you don't want that to happen, what do you do?
So, מקיצין בהן את המזבח, makiytzin bahen es hamizbeach, you use it
to keep the altar running, you use it to provide, you know,
summer runs to provide these עולות. olos. So again, the irony is
on the one hand it has קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf and on
the other hand you're selling it and using it for the קיץ
המזבח kayitz hamizbeach and תוספות Tosafos speaks about לב בית דין. lev
beis din. So that's one ברייתא. braisa. Anyway, that talks about the
overage. וקיץ זה מהו, vekayitz zeh mahu, what is this, what is
this, you know, this way of keeping the מזבח mizbeach around, this
dessert of the מזבח? mizbeach? עולות, olos, so they're עולות, olos, הבשר
לשם habasar l'hashem והעורות לכהנים. vehaoros l'kohanim. The flesh goes to God
and the skin to the כהנים. kohanim. Okay, interesting that it has
to spell that out. תניא כוותיה tanya kvassei דרבי יוחנן, de-Rabbi Yochanan,
we taught a ברייתא braisa like Rabbi Yochanan. מקבל עליו לספק סולת
מארבע mekabbel alav lesappek solos me'arba ועמדו משלוש ve'amdu mishalosh לספק בארבע.
lesappek be'arba. If you agreed at four and now it's three, you
have to still provide it at four. משלוש ועמדו מארבע, mishalosh ve'amdu
me'arba, if you provide agreed to do three and now it's at
four, לספק בארבע, lesappek be'arba, now you have to give the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash four. שיד הקדש על העליונה, sheyad hekdesh al haelyona,
that בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash always has the upper hand. וזהו ששנינו,
vezehu sheshanishnu, and this is what is meant in the ברייתא braisa
in another place where we teach מותר נסכים לקיץ המזבח, mosar nesachim
lekayitz hamizbeach, that the overage goes to supporting the running of the
מזבח mizbeach when things are slow. So this is where it comes
from. Okay, so that was interesting in terms of what you use
the overage for, but of course what's ironic is that you are
selling and redeeming even though that's one of the major things that's
not supposed to happen when it has קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Again,
what is really particularly interesting is number one, the idea that maybe
the whole קדושה kedusha was דרבנן derabbanan and the point about could
you wind up using it without, with you know, that way, I
think by at least wine is certainly something to think about. And
the other thing, which is I think what's really fascinating, is the
idea about that, you know, why should the dry measures not have
been sanctified, that is not being discussed at all. Okay, now we,
since we are talking so much around how to measure and all
these things, we suddenly have shifted a lot of our discussion, if
you might have noticed, from the מנחה mincha to the מנחת נסכים.
minchas nesachim. You know, and one of the reasons is because we're
also talking about wine, and we talked about where the wine used
to come from, that was in the last פרק. perek. So now
that we've been talking sort of around those issues, this משנה mishna
is finally going to get to bottom line, what exactly is the
obligation of מנחת נסכים? minchas nesachim? We've also mentioned by the way
the different amounts of the measures are, how much for the ox,
how much for the ram, whether it's the flour, whether it's the
oil. So a lot of the discussion has been around מנחת נסכים
minchas nesachim and this משנה mishna now turns towards it directly. So
let's take a look. כל קרבנות הצבור והיחיד טעונים נסכים, kol korbanos
hatzibbur vehayachid te'unim nesachim, all communal and private קרבנות korbanos get the,
get the libations. Libations means the wine plus the מנחה mincha of
the oil and the flour that the תורה Torah mentions in פנחס,
Pinchas, not פנחס, Pinchas, in שלח, Shelach, שלח Shelach I
think. חוץ chutz מן הבכור והמעשר והפסח min habechor vehamaser vehapesach except
for the firstborn animal, the מעשר, maaser, the פסח, pesach, וחטאת ואשם,
vechattas veasham, and the sin offering and the אשם. asham. So everything
except all of these. Of course, what are you left with? You
know what you're left with? The עולה olah and the שלמים. shelamim.
So I don't know why the משנה mishna did not say an
עולה olah and a שלמים shelamim get נסכים. nesachim. No, everything gets
נסכים nesachim except for the חטאת, chattas, the אשם, asham, the בכור,
bechor, the מעשר maaser and the פסח. pesach. I don't know. Anyway,
maybe because it allows... That's the contrast for the end of the
משנה, Mishna, אלא שחטאת מצורע ואשמו טעונים נסכים. Ella shechatat metzora veashamo
teunim nesachim. The one exception is there is a חטאת Chatat and
an אשם Asham that gets נסכים, Nesachim, and that is the מצורע,
Metzora, there the תורה Torah talks about it and we'll talk about
that in the גמרא. Gemara. So maybe it framed it this way
to make the contrast and say normally חטאת Chatat אשם Asham no,
yes for מצורע. Metzora.
Previous משניות Mishnas started כל. Kol.
Oh, maybe there's a whole, there's a whole thing going on, that's
interesting. Could be, כל מדות שבמקדש, Kol Midot Shebamikdash, that's interesting.
Yes. Except for the 14th of ניסן, Nisan, most קרבנות Korbanot are
going to be all over the place.
Right, so maybe the use of כל Kol is to emphasize how,
that it's the majority of קרבנות, Korbanot, not the majority of types
but the majority of the actual קרבנות Korbanot that are brought. That's
a good point. I mean, yeah, the תמידים Tamids are עולה, Olah,
a normal private קרבן Korban is an, I mean there are going
to be חטאות, Chatats, but I would imagine much more עולות Olos
and שלמים, Shelamim, right? And the מוספים Musafim are basically עולות Olos
except for the שעיר. Se'ir. So yeah, that's a good point.
The next one also starts כל הקרבנות.
Kol Hakorbanot. Yeah, that could also be literarily we're just doing hook-me.
Okay, that's a good point. That's a very good point. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
we taught, and so now we're going to interpret the פסוקים Psukim
about, all these פסוקים Psukim are right there in the תורה Torah
by the נסכים. Nesachim. So it says here, let me actually just
read a section of it.
I have it
here somewhere, top,
right here.
Oh, there you go. Thank you. So,
I
think this is in שלח Shlach if memory serves.
It is? Thank you. Okay.
Good to have some Bible people around when you're learning תלמוד. Talmud.
It's a פסוק Pasuk in מנחות. Menachos. Alright, anyway. So, דבר
אל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם כי תבאו אל ארץ מושבתיכם, Daber el
Bnei Yisrael ve'amarta aleihem ki tavo'u el Eretz moshvoteichem, which they weren't
חייב chayav in נסכים Nesachim until they came into ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, אשר אני נתן לכם, asher ani noten lachem, because you know
it's part of the produce of Israel. ועשיתם אשה לה' עלה או
זבח. Ve'asitem isheh l'Hashem Olah o Zevach. So an עולה Olah or
a זבח, Zevach, which we're going to interpret to mean is a
שלמים. Shelamim. So they are your major two categories that get נסכים,
Nesachim, an עולה או זבח, Olah o Zevach. לפלא נדר או בנדבה,
l'fale neder o vindavah, something that comes by a free-will vow. So
basically what we are going to say is even if an עולה
Olah comes as an obligation or שלמים Shelamim as an obligation, like
עולה Olah obligations you have as a תמיד, Tamid, you'd have as
מוספים, Musafim, or a שלמים Shelamim obligation is rarer, but you have
it for שבועות. Shavuot. So we're going, so although here it says
a זבח, Zevach, the גמרא's Gemara going to read it as, it
means the type of קרבן Korban that comes through a vow, not
that this, not that this particular one came through a vow. So
since עולה Olah and שלמים Shelamim are free-will קרבנות, Korbanot, they are
the type that comes through a vow, even if you're bringing it
as an obligation. So again, I'll read the פסוק Pasuk again, I'm
reading it sort of with rabbinic interpretation. Okay, so כי תבאו אל
ארץ מושבתיכם... ki tavo'u el Eretz moshvoteichem... ועשיתם אשה לה' עלה או
זבח. ve'asitem isheh l'Hashem Olah o Zevach. So an עולה Olah or
a שלמים, Shelamim, לפלא נדר או בנדבה, l'fale neder o vindavah, something
that came through a vow or dedication, meaning the type of קרבן
Korban that comes that way, again, עולה Olah or שלמים, Shelamim, או
במועדיכם o b'moadeichem on your holidays, so that is coming to tell
me that even when the עולה Olah and שלמים Shelamim are obligatory,
like they are as a מוסף, Musaf, certainly עולה Olah most of
the time, you still, you still bring it. לעשות ריח ניחח לה'
מן הבקר או מן הצאן. La'asot rei'ach nichoach l'Hashem min habakar o
min hatzon. Okay, and then it says then you bring the various
things. So we're going to have to ask why it has to
say בקר bakar and צאן, tzon, to exclude birds and so on.
That's going to be the whole ברייתא. Braita. Yes. Okay, alright, so
let's take a look now at the ברייתא. Braita. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, ועשיתם אשה לה', ve'asitem isheh l'Hashem, you make a, an offering
to God, a fire offering, יכול כל העלה לאשים, yachol kol ha-olah
l'ishim,
it's used as a verb, anything that's put on the fire, טעון
נסכים yetun Nesachim אפילו מנחה. afilu Mincha. So maybe the מנחה Mincha
itself gets the נסכים Nesachim and then maybe the מנחה Mincha of
the נסכים Nesachim gets its own מנחת נסכים? Minchat Nesachim? No, but
anyway, maybe even a מנחה, Mincha, which would be ironic. תלמוד לומר
Talmud lomar עולה. Olah So no, it gives you an example right
afterwards, it says an עולה. Olah. So we're talking about
animals.
אשה לה'. Isheh l'Hashem. Okay, skipped a lot. עולה, Olah. עולה. Olah,
So שלמים מנין? Shelamim minayin? So only animals, only an עולה. Olah.
So how do you know to include a שלמים? Shelamim? תלמוד לומר
Talmud lomar זבח. Zevach. So that's what it means עולה או זבח.
Olah o Zevach, זבח Zevach means a slaughtered thing, but it means
זבח Zevach is a שלמים. Shelamim. תודה מנין? Todah minayin? How do
you know about a תודה, Todah, which is a type of a
שלמים Shelamim but maybe it's here we have to be specific? תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar או זבח. o Zevach, So עולה או זבח, Olah
o zevach. not וזבח, ve-Zevach, means is more, somehow more inclusive, includes
even a תודה Todah which is a form of a שלמים. Shelamim.
יכול שאני מרבה אף בכור מעשר פסח? Yachol she-ani marbeh af bechor
ma'aser pesach? Maybe I'll include those? וחטאת ואשם? Ve-chatat ve-asham? And a
חטאת Chatat and אשם? Asham? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar לפלא נדר או
בנדבה. l'fale neder o vindavah. So now that we've started including, you
needed the next part of the פסוק Pasuk to be clearer to
limit. So בא בנדר ובנדבה טעון נסכים. Ba b'neder u-vindavah teun Nesachim.
Only something that could come through a vow. What are the only
קרבנות Korbanot that could come through a free-will vow? An עולה Olah.
and a שלמים. Shelamim. A בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser, and פסח, pesach,
although in some ways they're שלמים-like Shelamim and they're קדשים קלים, kodshim
kalim, but they come only through obligations, they can never come through
vows, and certainly not a חטאת Chatat and an אשם. Asham. So
שאינו בא בנדר ובנדבה, she-eino ba b'neder u-vindavah, if it does not
come through a vow, אין טעון נסכים, ein teun Nesachim, does not
get the, does not get the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. Okay. משמע
להוציא את אלו. Mashma l'hotzi et eleh. So now I know to
exclude those. So once I'm excluding those, הוציא את חובות הבאות מחמת
הרגל. hotzi et chovot haba'ot machamat ha-regel. Let me exclude the obligatory
sacrifice on the רגל regel even. even when they're an עולה. Olah
If I'm really making a difference about is it coming through a
vow or not, let me take it literally and exclude the עולה
Olah. that comes as an obligation as a מוסף Musaf ברגל. B'regel.
ומהינהו, U'mainihu, עולת ראיה Olas re'iyah and שלמי חגיגה. Shalmei chagigah. Interesting
actually, by the way, it doesn't even go to the מוספים, Musafim,
which would be more obvious.
I think the reason it doesn't go to the מוספים Musafim is
because there's פסוקים Psukim in פנחס Pinchas that make it clear that
there's a נסך. Nesach.
Right, that's a good point. That's a good point. So maybe I
would have just thought that only at the individual level, at the
communal level, right, okay, so side hike, although later we're going to
also talk about the, yes, okay, but good. Side hike, right. So
I think, I think the point is very well-taken that the גמרא
Gemara is not discussing the, I was jumping to the מוסף, Musaf,
but the מוסף Musaf is clear you do, but those are פסוקים,
Psukim, so that's not the הוה אמינא. Hava amina. The הוה אמינא
Hava amina would be to exclude the obligations, but the private obligations
of an עולה Olah and שלמים. Shlamim. Where are there private obligations
of an עולה Olah and שלמים? Shlamim? To bring the עולת ראיה,
Olas re'iyah, יראה כל זכורך Yera'eh kol zechurcha means through an עולה,
Olah and the שלמי חגיגה Shalmei chagigah when it says וחגותם אותו
חג לה', V'chagosem oso chag l'Hashem, they're supposed to rejoice on the
רגל, Regel, we understand that means through the bringing of שלמים. Shlamim.
So those are private obligations on the רגל, Regel, maybe because it's
obligatory, maybe I don't bring the נסכים. Nesachim. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
או במועדיכם, O bemoadeichem, or on your holidays, כל הבא במועדיכם, Kol
haba bemoadeichem, anything coming on your holidays, again if it satisfies the
other criteria that it's an עולה Olah, and a שלמים, Shlamim, then
it is טעון נסכים, Taun nesachim, then you bring the נסכים. Nesachim.
Okay, so now what do I know? I know that it has
to be something that can come through a vow, עולה, Olah שלמים,
Shlamim, not בכור, Bechor, מעשר, Maaser, פסח, Pesach, not אשם Asham and
חטאת, Chatas, can come through a vow, but then even when it
comes through an obligation even at the private level, like the עולת
ראיה Olas re'iyah and שלמי חגיגה. Shalmei chagigah. So good, that's where
we needed to get. What's left? So משמע להביא את אלו. Mashma
l'havi es elu. Now I know to include those. אביא שעירי חטאת,
Avia se'irei chatat, maybe I'll also include the goats of the חטאת,
Chatat, הואיל ובאין חובה ברגל, Ho'ilu u'va'in chova b'regel, since those are
obligatory on the רגל, Regel, and here we do shift to the
communal, but as, you know, the point being made, you know, Marty's
point was that it's explicit that you bring it with the עולות
Olos of the מוספים. Musafim. It doesn't, the תורה Torah doesn't say
you bring it with the חטאת, Chatat, for a good reason, you
don't bring it with חטאת. Chatat. But now we're saying okay, maybe
it's saying everything that comes on a רגל Regel and everything includes
even the חטאת, Chatat, even the goat for the חטאת. Chatat. So
שעירי רגלים, Se'irei regalim, חטאת, Chatat, הואיל ובאין חובה ברגל, Ho'ilu u'va'in
chova b'regel, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, וכי תעשה בן בקר, V'chi saaseh
ben bakar, because it says, because it also says at the beginning,
if you make a cattle as an עולה Olah, or זבח. Zevach.
So why does it say cattle? בן בקר בכלל היה. Ben bakar
bikhlal haya. So it was already included, we already basically included everything
we needed to. Why does the תורה Torah spell out cattle? ולמה
יצא? V'lamah yatza? Why was it singled out? להקיש לו, Lehikish lo,
to connect to it, to use it as a paradigm. מה בן
בקר מיוחד בא בנדר ובנדבה, אף כל בא בנדר ובנדבה, Mah ben
bakar meyuchad ba b'neder u'vindava, af kol ba b'neder u'vindava, the same
way בן בקר Ben bakar is distinguished that it can come through
a vow, אף כל בא בנדר ובנדבה. Af kol ba b'neder u'vindava.
Only things that come through vows, not goats, now of course it's
bizarre because a cow can also come as an obligation, right? You
can have a בן בקר לחטאת, Ben bakar l'chatas, a שעיר Se'ir
can come as an עולה. Olah So it's not really, you know,
distinctive of the cattle that it's only free will. So רש"י Rashi
says well, it's because the תורה Torah says בן בקר עולה או
זבח. Ben bakar olah o zevach. So in this context, בן בקר
Ben bakar has been identified as a type of a נדר. Neder.
Of course once you're saying that, why go to בן בקר? Ben
bakar? Why not just say we already said עולה או לפלא נדר
או לנדבה, Olah o l'falei neder o l'vindava, which means it has
to be of the type that comes through an obligation. So it's
a little strange how it's using בן בקר. Ben bakar. Okay, לעשות,
Laasot, now try to just finish the ברייתא, Brayta, לעשות ריח ניחוח
לה', Laasot reiach nichoach l'Hashem, as a pleasing aroma to God, מן
הבקר ומן הצאן, Min habakar u'min hatzon, from the cattle and the
sheep. So again, why do you have to say cattle and sheep?
מה תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar? Why is it, what is it
teaching me? לפי שנאמר, L'fi shene'emar, עולה. Olah. It already said עולה.
Olah. שומע אני אפילו עולת העוף במשמע. Shome'a ani afilu olas ha'of
b'mashma. Ah, that maybe I would have thought. How about a bird
עולה? Olah. That's free will, that's an עולה, Olah? that was a
reasonable thing to think. תלמוד לומר מן הבקר ומן הצאן. Talmud lomar
min habakar u'min hatzon. No, that's why it says at the end
sheep and cattle, only like big animals. דברי רבי יאשיה. Divrei Rabbi
Yoshiya. That only mammals. That's what רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says. רבי
יונתן אומר אינו צריך. Rabbi Yonasan omer eino tzarikh. I don't need
to learn it from there. הרי הוא אומר, Harei hu omer, זבח.
Zevach. It says עולה Olah, או זבח. o Zevach. And what's a
זבח? Zevach? Something slaughtered with a knife, as opposed to a bird
which you do with your finger, which isn't slaughtered. העוף אינו זבח.
Ha'of eino zevach. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר מן הבקר ומן הצאן?
Im kein mah talmud lomar min habakar u'min hatzon? So according to
you that we already know to exclude birds, why does it say
sheep and cattle? לפי שנאמר, L'fi shene'emar, אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן
לה' מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם, Adam ki
yakriv mikem korban l'Hashem min habiheima min habakar u'min hatzon takrivu es
korbanchem, going back to the very beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, if anybody
brings from you a קרבן Korban to God,
מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם, Min habiheima min
habakar u'min hatzon takrivu es korbanchem, from the sheep and the cattle.
So I might have read that verse, the ו' Vav as an
'and', not an 'or'. If
you want to bring an animal, it must be מן הבקר ומן
הצאן, Min habakar u'min hatzon, you have to bring both an ox,
you know, a cattle and a sheep. יכול אפילו אומר הרי עלי
עולה, יביא משניהם, Yakhol afilu omer harei alai olah, yavi mishneihem, maybe
a person who just generally says I'll bring an עולה, Olah, יביא
משניהם, Yavi mishneihem, maybe you have to bring both מן הבקר ומן
הצאן, Min habakar u'min hatzon, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, that's why it
says here by נסכים Nesachim to teach you something way
back. So here it stuck in the או o to teach you
that way back in the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra it meant or,
not and. So רוצה אחד מביא, rotzeh echad meivi, רוצה שנים מביא.
rotzeh shnayim meivi. If you want you can bring one, if you
want you can bring both. The ו vav way back then meant
or, did not mean and. Okay, and we will pick up with
analyzing this tomorrow.